Finding Aid for Thomas James O’Brien papers, 1877-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas James O’Brien papers 1877-1933
O’Brien, Thomas James, 1842-1933.
851950 Aa 2; AC; Ac; UAm
U.S. Ambassador to Japan, 1907-1911, and Italy, 1911-1913. Ledgers and journals, scrapbooks/photograph albums containing clippings, photographs and mementos from his diplomatic career, and miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, and speech material.
3 linear feet
10 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Howard O’Brien (donor no. 2209 ) and came to the library in 1946.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas James O'Brien was born July 30, 1842 in Jackson County, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1899 as part of the class of 1865 (nunc pro tunc). He was admitted to the Bar in 1865, and began the practice of law, first in Marshall, then in Grand Rapids, Michigan.
O'Brien was a Republican, running unsuccessfully to become justice on the Michigan Supreme Court in 1883. In 1905, President Roosevelt appointed O'Brien to be US minister to Denmark. He served here for nearly two years to negotiate the cession of the Danish West Indies to the United States. In 1907, he was appointed ambassador to Japan. In 1909, he was offered ambassadorial appointments to Russian and Turkey, but chose to remain in Japan. In 1911, he accepted appointment to Italy, remaining in that post until 1913. He then reopened his law practice.
He died May 19, 1933.
The Thomas James O’Brien papers consist of ledgers and journals, scrapbooks/photograph albums containing clippings, photographs and mementos from his diplomatic career, and miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, and speech material. The Collection has been arranged into the following series: Scrapbooks / Photograph Albums; Financial records; and Correspondence and other papers.
Subjects:
Denmark.; Diplomats.; Italy.; Japan.; O'Brien, Thomas James, 1842-1933.; United States--Foreign relations--Italy.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--History--1861-1912.; Denmark.; Diplomats.; International relations.; Japan.; O'Brien, Thomas James, 1842-1933.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.
Contributors:
Howard, William Alanson, 1813-1880.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks / Photograph Albums
  - Miscellaneous
    - [Vol. A] circa 1870-1880 (Box 1)
      (volume of obituaries of William A. Howard, father of Delia Howard, Mrs. Thomas J. O'Brien; also materials related to O'Brien)
    - [Vol. B] 1930s (Box 1)
      (Unorganized scrapbook including clippings about O'Brien and his family, obituaries, some early photographs of O'Brien, some photographs of Japan including photos of a fourth of July banquet at Yokohama, 1910)
  - Diplomatic career: Denmark
    - [Vol. C] 1905 (Box 1)
      (Newspaper clippings and correspondence regarding his appointment as minister to Denmark (appointed March 5, 1905); letters of congratulations, letters from O'Brien to his son Howard, photographs of Denmark)
  - Diplomatic career: Japan
    (microfilm copy of these volumes is available)
    - [Vol. D] Photograph Album, undated (Box 1)
      (Unidentified photograph album with scenes of Japanese gardens and portraits of a Japanese family)
    - [Vol. 1] 1907 (Volume 1)
      (Newspaper clippings regarding his appointment as ambassador to Japan (appointed June 11, 1907) and his activities in Japan)
    - [Vol. 2] 1907 (Volume 2)
      (Photographs of the trip to Japan with William Howard Taft, reception at court and other Japanese scenes; also many calling cards, menus, programs, invitations and other memorabilia.)
    - [Vol. 3] January-May 1908 (Volume 3)
      (Programs, calling cards, invitations and occasional photographs of Japan.)
    - [Vol. 8] June-December 1908 (Volume 8)
      (Photographs of Russia and England and of the coming of the U.S. Fleet to Yokohama, Japan in October 1908 also memorabilia (organized in reverse chronological order))
    - [Vol. 7] January 1908-October 1909 (Volume 7)
      (Newspaper clippings regarding O'Brien's activities as Ambassador to Japan)
    - [Vol. 9] January-June 1909 (Volume 9)
      (Photographs of England, Siberia, and Japan and memorabilia)
    - [Vol. 10] 1909 (Volume 10)
      (Primarily photographs of Japan, including excellent interior views of the American Embassy and good candid shots of the Ambassador's life and scenes of Japanese life; also photographs of a trip to China, March 1909)
    - [Vol. 4] 1910 (Volume 4)
      (Programs, invitations, menus, and occasional postcards of Japanese scenes)
    - [Vol. 5] January-March 1911 (Volume 5)
      (Programs, invitations, menus, and photographs, including photographs of the Imperial Duck Hunt in March 1911)
- Financial records
  - Journals
    - April 27, 1880-1883 (Box 2)
    - 1883-May 1886 (Box 2)
    - June 1886-January 1889 (Box 2)
    - January 1889-1892 (Box 2)
    - 1893-June 1896 (Box 2)
    - July 1896-February 1897 (Box 2)
    - 1902-December 1912 (Volume 6)
  - Ledger
    - 1877-1883 (Box 3)
    - 1883-1885 (Box 3)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and other papers
  - Correspondence largely of Mrs. T.J. O'Brien 1889-1898 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence of O'Brien and others 1905-1909 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence concerning in part change in positions from Japan, and Italian controversy over the use of benzine 1909-1922 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous letters to the editor and interviews (Box 3)
  - Notes for speeches (Box 3)
  - Papers re. Japan and U.S.-Japanese relations (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
    (see also oversize folder, UAm)
  - Citations and diplomas, 5 items (Folder AC)